Psychology Collection, 1967-1984
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Psychology collection
1967-1984
MS 449
14 boxes, 8 volumes (8 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The collection includes general writings pertaining to the psychology of women; counseling women; and sex role stereotypes, including gender dysphoria syndrome and transsexualism. There are also eleven boxes of resource materials used by Richard Tresemer for his work entitled "Gender and the Fear of Success" on psychological development and gender roles and how they relate to achievement and success. Materials include bibliographies, articles, pamphlets, abstracts, and dissertations.
The Psychology Collection is comprised of bibliographies, articles, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, abstracts, and dissertations. It includes general writings pertaining to the psychology of women; counseling women, and sex role stereotypes, including gender dysphoria syndrome and transsexualism. In addition, there are eleven boxes of resource materials (articles, manuscripts and papers) used by Richard Tresemer for his work entitled "Gender and the Fear of Success" on psychological development and gender roles and how they relate to achievement and success.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Note: this collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
History of the Collection
Materials in this subject collection were either purchased or given to the Sophia Smith Collection by various donors. The "Gender and the Fear of Success" materials were donated by Richard Tresemer.
Search Terms
Gender identity--United States--Psychological aspects; Sex role--United States--History--20th century; Stereotypes (Psychology)--United States; Success--United States--History-20th century--Sources; Transsexuals--United States--Psychology; Women--Counseling of; Women--United States--Psychology--Sources; Women--Mental health--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Tresemer, David Ward. Fear of success (1977) -- Sources
- General (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Fear of success (Box 1, Folder 2)
  [See also boxes 4-13]
- Bibliographies
  - General (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Psychology of Women by Joyce Jennings Walsted 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Women and Psychology" (Box 1)
- Articles (alphabetical by author) (Box 1, Folder 5-9)
- Women in psychology: general (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Counseling
    - General (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - The Counseling Psychologist: Counseling Women vol. 4 #1 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Freud, Sigmund (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Spock, Benjamin (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Therapy (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Women's Role Conflicts and Mental Health by Barbara Czesick (thesis) 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- A Biosocial Perspective on Parenting by Anne S. Rossi undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Women and Men: Roles, Attitudes and Power Relationships by Eleanor Zuckerman 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Sex differences: clippings and articles (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Sex role stereotypes
  - Articles (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Clippings (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Greeting cards (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Transsexualism (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "Gender Roles and Fear of Success": research materials collected by Richard Tresemer (Box 4-13)
  [See separate list in box 4]
- Books on Shelf
  - Astin, Helen S., Sex Roles: A Research Bibliography 1975
  - Horner, M., Sex Difference in Achievement Motification and Performance 1968
  - House, G.F., Orientations to Achievement and Autonomous Social Comparison... 1973
  - Kavanaugh, James and Everett Shostrom, Between Men and Women 1971
  - Tec, Leon, The Fear of Success 1976
  - Thompson, C.J.D., The Mysteries of Sex: Women Who Posed as Men and Men Who Impersonated Women 1974
  - Tresemer, David Ward, Fear of Success 1977
  - Tresemer, David Ward, Success Avoidance and Gender Role 1974